Norman C. Southergill VHP2005/7
CCSU Veterans History Project
Norman C. Southergill Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1943-1945, 1952, 2005
VHP2005/7
CCSU Veterans History Project
73.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This Collection details Norman Southergill’s military history and recollections during his enlistment in World War II as a member of the 150th Combat Engineer Battalion. He served in the European theatre during World War II building, repairing and dismantling bridges, clearing and setting land mines, and ferrying troops. While not in direct combat, mortar, tank and sniper attacks were common occurrences for the troops building bridges.
Southergill, Norman C., (Norman Clarence ), 1924 -
Biographical/Historical note
Norman C. Southergill was drafted into the U.S. Army in March of 1943. He originally volunteered for the Army Air Corps; however, the army placed him in an engineering battalion instead. Southergill was a tool keeper, and he was sent to West Virginia to train in combat engineering. His unit specialized in building temporary bridges, laying mines, and sweeping mines. From West Virginia, his unit went to Fort Dix, and subsequently sailed to Gloucester, England on the Queen Mary, which took 11 days. Southergill stayed in England for six months while his battalion did additional training and built an airport. In July of 1944, his unit landed in Normandy, where they maintained the roads and bridges that were under U.S. control. It was at this time that his unit became part of Patton's third army, and the soldiers constructed miles of bridges across France and Germany. After the war in Europe ended, Southergill was transferred to an artillery unit, where he was charged with building a garage using the labor of German prisoners of war. When he was discharged in November of 1945, he returned to Connecticut, and learned how to paint, among other skills, on the G.I. Bill. He also wrote a book about his experiences in the army and became a second lieutenant in the CT State Guard. Southergill has kept in touch with his battalion through annual reunions.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army. Engineer Combat Battalion, 150th.; United States. Army.; England; Fort Devens (Mass.); Fort Dix (N.J.); France; Germany; Interviews; Manuscript; Photographs; Prisoners of war -- Germany; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Europe; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/7.I
  - Notice to Registrant to Appear for Physical Examination, Jan. 29, 1943; VHP2005/7.I.1; 2.0 Digital files
  - Order to report for induction, Feb. 26, 1943; VHP2005/7.I.2
  - Honorable Discharge, Dec. 3, 1945; VHP2005/7.I.3
  - Discharge Papers and Separation Documents (from WD AGO 53-55), Dec. 3, 1945; VHP2005/7.I.4
  - Interview Sysnopsis, Jun. 17, 2005; VHP2005/7.I.5; 3.0 pages
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2005/7.II
  - Commendation message from M.S. EDDY, Major General, U.S. army to XII Corps Troops. And highlights of the 150th Engineer Combat Battalion while with XII Corps., Apr. 20, 1945; VHP2005/7.II.1; 4.0 pages
- Series III: Publications, VHP2005/7.III
  - 150th Engineer Combat Battalion History: February 1943 - May 1945, n.d.; VHP2005/7.III.1; 55.0 pages
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2005/7.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/7.IVa
    - Portrait of Norman Southergill in Army uniform, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.1
    - Group photo of 1st Infantry Regimentt Officers, "Camp lodge Niantic", July 1952; VHP2005/7.IV.2
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.3; 55.0
    - Building labled "Gestapo", Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.4; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.5; 55.0
    - Dummy German officers inside mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.6; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.7; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.8; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.9; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.10; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.11; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.12; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.13; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.14; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.15; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.16; 55.0
    - Mockup German Village at Camp Edwards, MA, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.17; 55.0
    - Norman Southergill with an unknown woman. Elkens, West Virginia, 1943; VHP2005/7.IV.18; 55.0
    - Red Cross Volunteers, France, 1944; VHP2005/7.IV.19; 55.0
    - Red Cross Volunteers, France, 1944; VHP2005/7.IV.20; 55.0
    - Red Cross Volunteers serving coffee and donuts, France, 1944; VHP2005/7.IV.21; 55.0
    - Red Cross Volunteers serving coffee and donuts, France, 1944; VHP2005/7.IV.22; 55.0
    - (L to R) Norman Southergill, Mike Hebda, Germany, 1944; VHP2005/7.IV.23; 55.0
    - Group photo, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.24
      General note
      Back row (L to R): Mike Hebda, Norman Southergill, Albert Fredericks and Herbert Rollins. Front row (L to R): Larry Henault and Billy Crooks.
    - (L to R) Edmund Borge, unknown, Larry Henault, Albert Fredericks, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.25
    - (L to R) Edmund Borge, unknown, Larry Henault, Albert Fredericks, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.26
    - Work crew, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.27
    - Norman Southergill, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.28
    - James Faille, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.29
    - (L to R) Back row: Henry Densky,James Faille, Larry Henault, Albert Fredericks. Front row: Billy, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.30
    - (L to R) Back row: Henry Densky, Norman Southergill, Front row: James Faille, unknown, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.31
    - (L to R) the barber is Lynch, Robert Sanborn (getting haircut), Daniel Donabecian, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.32
    - Norman Southergill, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.33
    - Henry Densky, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.34
    - Soldiers in Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.35
    - Work crew, Luxembourg, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.36
    - Floating treadway bridge over the Danube River Built by the 150th Combat Engineers. Straubing, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.37
    - Soldiers in Regensburg, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.38
    - (L to R) Larry Heneault, Norman Southergill, Albert Fredericks. Czechoslovakia, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.39
    - Troops boarding train to Belgium, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.40
    - Sights on the way back to Belgium, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.41
    - Sights on the way back to Belgium, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.42
    - Sights on the way back to Belgium, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.43
    - Sights on the way back to Belgium, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.44
    - Floating tread way bridge over the Danube river. Built by the 150th Combat Engineers, Straubing, Germany, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.45
    - Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.46
    - Troops on a boat. Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.47
    - Eiffel Tower, Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.48
    - Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.49
    - Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.50
    - Street of Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.51
    - Swimming in the Seine river, Paris, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.52
    - Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.53
    - Boarding practice ladder, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.54
    - Company Street, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.55
    - Company Street, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.56
    - Norman Southergill’s tent ,Company Street ,Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.57
    - Amphitheatre where movies were shown. Site created by natural erosion, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.58
    - Amphitheatre where movies were shown. Site created by natural erosion, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.59
    - Amphitheatre where movies were shown. Site created by natural erosion, Marseille, France, 1945; VHP2005/7.IV.60
    - U.S.S Pontotac 1945. Victory Ship on the way home., VHP2005/7.IV.61
      Victory Ship on the way home. (L to R) unknown, store keeper, unknown. Norman Southergill was a store keeper’s assistant
    - Norman Southergill’s medals, 2005; VHP2005/7.IV.62
    - Norman Southergill’s souvenirs, 2005; VHP2005/7.IV.63
    - Norman Southergill’s reunion, Southergill is third from right in the back row., 2005; VHP2005/7.IV.64
    - Norman Southergill, 2005; VHP2005/7.IV.65
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2005/7.IVb
    - Oral History Interview, June 17, 2005; VHP2005/7.IVb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/7, Box VHP Interview #1)